Linjian Ma

+1 217 979 7114 \$\displays \text{lma16@illinois.edu} \$\displays \text{linjianma.github.io}\$ github/Linkedin: linjianma

RESEARCH STATEMENT

My research interests lie in the intersection of numerical algorithms, high performance computing and quantum computing. In particular, I'm now focusing on developing efficient numerical algorithms and parallel systems for tensor computations with applications in quantum algorithms, quantum simulation and data analytics. Previously, I worked on optimization and efficient compression methods of neural networks.

EDUCATION BACKGROUNDS

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2019 - Expected 2023

PhD, Computer Science, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

GPA: 3.95/4.0

GPA: 3.97/4.0

GPA: 3.95/4.0

Area: Scientific Computing

University of California, Berkeley

August 2018 - May 2019

MEng, Computer Science, Advisor: Michael Mahoney

Major GPA: 3.94/4.0

Track: Data Science & Systems

University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign

August 2016 - May 2018

MS, Mechanical Engineering, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Concentration: Computational Science and Engineering

Zhejiang University August 2012 - June 2016

BE, Energy Engineering, Advisor: Tao Wang and Zhongyang Luo

Graduate with Honors, Chu Kochen Honors College

EXPERIENCES

Lab for Parallel Numerical Algorithms, UIUC

August 2019 - Now

Research Assistant, Advisor: Edgar Solomonik

Topic: On efficient algorithms and systems for numerical tensor algebra

Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory

May 2020 - August 2020

Research Intern, Advisor: Chao Yang

Topic: Analyzing quantum algorithms based on low-rank approximation

Wave Computing & Berkeley AI Research (BAIR)

May 2019 - August 2019

Machine Learning Intern

Topic: Compressing large scale neural networks based on second-order information

RiseLab, UC Berkeley

August 2018 - May 2019

Research Assistant, Advisor: Michael Mahoney

Capstone project: Second-order optimization of neural network learning

Beckman Institute, UIUC

August 2016 - December 2017

Research Assistant, Advisor: N.R. Aluru

Thesis: A multiscale model for the oxide ion conducting and proton conducting solid oxide cells

SKILLS

Programming Languages ML Frameworks

C/C++, Python, Go, Bash, Matlab, CUDA

Pytorch, TensorFlow

PUBLICATIONS

- [1] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Efficient Parallel CP Decomposition with Pairwise Perturbation and Multisweep Dimension Tree, *International Parallel and Distributed Processing Symposium (IPDPS'21)*, 2021. [link]
- [2] **Linjian Ma***, Jiayu Ye*, and Edgar Solomonik, AutoHOOT: Automatic High-Order Optimization for Tensors, International Conference on Parallel Architectures and Compilation Techniques (PACT'20), 2020. [link]
- [3] Sheng Shen, Zhen Dong, Jiayu Ye, **Linjian Ma**, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Michael W. Mahoney, Kurt Keutzer, Q-BERT: Hessian Based Ultra Low Precision Quantization of BERT, AAAI'20, 2020. [link]
- [4] **Linjian Ma***, Gabe Montague*, Jiayu Ye*, Zhewei Yao, Amir Gholami, Kurt Keutzer, Michael W. Mahoney, Inefficiency of K-FAC for Large Batch Size Training, AAAI'20, 2020. [link]
- [5] Navjot Singh, **Linjian Ma**, Hongru Yang, Edgar Solomonik, Comparison of Accuracy and Scalability of Gauss-Newton and Alternating Least Squares for CP Decomposition, arXiv:1910.12331, 2019. [link]
- [6] **Linjian Ma** and Edgar Solomonik, Accelerating Alternating Least Squares for Tensor Decomposition by Pairwise Perturbation, arXiv:1811.10573, 2018. [link]
- [7] **Linjian Ma**, A Multiscale Model for the Oxide Ion Conducting and Proton Conducting Solid Oxide Cells, *MS thesis*, *University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign*, 2018. [link]
- [8] **Linjian Ma**, Pikee Priya, and N. R. Aluru, A Multiscale Model for Electrochemical Reactions in LSCF Based Solid Oxide Cells, *Journal of the Electrochemical Society*, 2018. [link]

HONORS AND AWARDS

Kuck Computational Science & Engineering Scholarship, UIUC	2020
Computer Science Gene Golub Fellowship, UIUC	2019
Graduate with Honor, ZJU	2016
Meritorious Winner, Mathematical Contest In Modeling (MCM)	2015
National Scholarship for Undergraduate, ZJU	2014
The First Class Scholarship for Outstanding Students, ZJU	2013 - 2014
The First Prize in China Undergraduates Mathematical Contest	2013

PRESENTATIONS

Upcoming presentations
First author presentations
Posters

SIAM'LA 2021, SIAM'CSE 2021, IPDPS 2021

PACT 2020, SIAM'PP 2020, Berkeley'SCseminar 2019, USNCCM 2017

SIAM'PP 2020, AAAI 2020

SERVICES

Teaching Assistant

CS 450 Numerical Analysis (Fall 2020)